<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>XploR Studio – RTOS Views</title><link>/docs/features/views/</link><description>Recent content in RTOS Views on XploR Studio</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 08:49:15 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/docs/features/views/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Docs: FreeRTOS views</title><link>/docs/features/views/freertos/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2020 15:21:01 +0200</pubDate><guid>/docs/features/views/freertos/</guid><description>
&lt;p>During the FreeRTOS debug sessions, developers need to examine the state of the applications. This state can be seen as Task, Queue, Heap, and Timer. The following sessions describe how XploR Studio helps to check this information.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Note:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>To open FreeRTOS Objects View, select &lt;strong>Windows &amp;gt; Show View &amp;gt; Others&lt;/strong>. In &lt;strong>Show View&lt;/strong> wizard, select &lt;strong>FreeRTOS Object Views&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The FreeRTOS object views only contain information when user debugs a FreeRTOS project&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Depending on the FreeRTOS application, not all FreeRTOS objects will display valid information. For example, if the application does not utilize a Timer object, XploR Studio will not display any useful information on FreeRTOS Timer view.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The display of FreeRTOS views is dependent on the &lt;strong>xplor-studio-freertos-debug-plugin&lt;/strong> component. Therefore, if you uninstall this component, please close these views to prevent any errors.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="freertos-task-view">FreeRTOS Task View&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The FreeRTOS task view helps developers examine tasks during debug sessions. Each object is identified by its ID, name, address, state, task state, stack usage, event object, runtime, and priority.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images_views/freertos/20.png" alt="example image">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="freertos-queue-view">FreeRTOS Queue View&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The FreeRTOS Queue view helps developers examine queues during debug sessions. Each object is identified by its type, ID, name, address, length, size, and state of TX and RX.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images_views/freertos/21.png" alt="example image">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="freertos-timer-view">FreeRTOS Timer View&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The FreeRTOS Timer view helps developers examine timers during debug sessions. Each object is identified by its ID, name, status, callback functions, and similar.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images_views/freertos/22.png" alt="example image">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="freertos-heap-view">FreeRTOS Heap View&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The FreeRTOS Heap view helps developers examine heaps during debug sessions. Each object is identified by its ID, address, usage information, and similar.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images_views/freertos/23.png" alt="example image">&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Docs: Zephyr OS views</title><link>/docs/features/views/zephyrtos/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2020 15:21:01 +0200</pubDate><guid>/docs/features/views/zephyrtos/</guid><description>
&lt;p>During the ZephyrRTOS debug sessions, developers need to examine the state of the applications. This state can be seen as Thread, Mutex, Semaphore, and MessageQueue. The following sessions describe how XploR Studio helps to check this information.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Note:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>To open ZephyrRTOS Objects View, select &lt;strong>Windows &amp;gt; Show View &amp;gt; Other&amp;hellip;&lt;/strong>. In &lt;strong>Show View&lt;/strong> wizard, select &lt;strong>ZephyrRTOS Object Views&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The ZephyrRTOS object views only contain information when user debugs a ZephyrRTOS project&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Depending on the ZephyrRTOS application, not all ZephyrRTOS objects will display valid information. For example, if the application does not utilize a Mutex object, XploR Studio will not display any useful information on ZephyrRTOS Mutex view.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The display of ZephyrRTOS views is dependent on the &lt;strong>xplor-studio-zephyr-debug-plugin&lt;/strong> component. Therefore, if you uninstall this component, please close these views to prevent any errors.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="zephyrrtos-thread-view">ZephyrRTOS Thread View&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The ZephyrRTOS Thread view helps developers examine threads during debug sessions. Each object is identified by its ID, Name, Handle, Priority, Thread State and Thread Usage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images_views/zephyrtos/1.png" alt="example image">&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Note:&lt;/strong> This image is sourced from the Zephyr Hello World project. However, please note that for other projects, the view may vary or unavailable.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="zephyrrtos-mutex-view">ZephyrRTOS Mutex View&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The ZephyrRTOS Mutex view helps developers examine mutexes during debug sessions. Each object is identified by its ID, Handle, Mutex Owner, Owner Priority and Lock Count.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images_views/zephyrtos/2.png" alt="example image">&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Note:&lt;/strong> This image is sourced from the Zephyr Mutex project. However, please note that for other projects, the view may vary or unavailable.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="zephyrrtos-semaphore-view">ZephyrRTOS Semaphore View&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The ZephyrRTOS Semaphore view helps developers examine semaphores during debug sessions. Each object is identified by its ID, Handle, Semaphore Count and Semaphore Limit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images_views/zephyrtos/3.png" alt="example image">&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Note:&lt;/strong> This image is sourced from the Zephyr Semaphore project. However, please note that for other projects, the view may vary or unavailable.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="zephyrrtos-message-queue-view">ZephyrRTOS Message Queue View&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The ZephyrRTOS Message Queue view helps developers examine message queues during debug sessions. Each object is identified by its ID, Handle, Message Size, Max Messages, Read Pointer, Write Pointer, Used Messages and Flags.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images_views/zephyrtos/4.png" alt="example image">&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Note:&lt;/strong> This image is sourced from the Zephyr Message Queue project. However, please note that for other projects, the view may vary or unavailable.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item></channel></rss>