<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>XploR Studio – Getting Started</title><link>/docs/getting-started/</link><description>Recent content in Getting Started on XploR Studio</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 08:49:15 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/docs/getting-started/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Docs: Concepts</title><link>/docs/getting-started/concepts/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2020 15:21:01 +0200</pubDate><guid>/docs/getting-started/concepts/</guid><description>
&lt;h2 id="cross-platform-development">Cross-platform development&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In embedded development, the compute architecture of the &lt;strong>host development system&lt;/strong> (i.e. &lt;em>hosts&lt;/em>) is different than the the &lt;strong>target execution platform&lt;/strong> (i.e. &lt;em>targets&lt;/em>). Thus, the &lt;strong>target application(s)&lt;/strong> (i.e. &lt;em>programs&lt;/em>) will not be able to run on the host development system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;strong>communication channel&lt;/strong> between the host and target provides the means for the host software (e.g. XploR Studio) to program and control the target hardware implementation and programs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Because of the inherent architural differences between the hosts and targets, &lt;strong>XploR Studio&lt;/strong> is integrated with different embedded compiler toolchains, operating systems, hardware designs, and debug &amp;amp; monitoring tools, packaged as &lt;strong>blueprints&lt;/strong> and delivered by the IDE to provide a unified experience to create, build, deploy, test and debug designs for developers.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-plantuml" data-lang="plantuml">mainframe Cross-platform development
state &amp;#34;Host Development System&amp;#34; as hosts
note left of hosts : where XploR IDE runs
hosts : Linux or Windows on x86 / ia64
state &amp;#34;Target Execution Platforms&amp;#34; as targets
targets : ARM, RISC-V, or others ISA(s)\nrunning baremetal or with an\nembedded OS
note right of targets : where target applications run
targets -u-&amp;gt; hosts
note left on link
acknowledgement to
host from target
end note
hosts --&amp;gt; targets
note left on link
host commands to
program or debug target
end note
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h2 id="embedded-target">Embedded Target&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In the post-silicon development flow, the &lt;strong>embedded target&lt;/strong> consists of a CPU and associated peripherals (e.g. USB, Ethernet, I2C, &amp;hellip;). The CPU implements and execute code defined by an Instruction Set Architecture (ISA, e.g. x86, ARM, RISC-V). &lt;strong>JTAG&lt;/strong> is commonly the communication channel between the host and target for programming and debugging, as shown below:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-plantuml" data-lang="plantuml">mainframe Post-silicon embedded target
state &amp;#34;Host Development System&amp;#34; as hosts
hosts : Linux or Windows on x86 / ia64
state &amp;#34;Target Platform (ASICs)&amp;#34; as targets {
state CPU : x86 or ARM
state Memory : DDR, SRAM, ...
state Peripherals : USB, Ethernet, ...
}
note bottom of targets : CPU, Memory and Peripherals are\nASIC blocks, not modifable.
state JTAG
note top of JTAG : JTAG used to program target memory\nand control / debug programs on CPU.
hosts -&amp;gt; JTAG
JTAG -&amp;gt; targets
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h2 id="target-execution-platform">Target execution platform&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>With the advent of open source CPU implementation (e.g. &lt;a href="https://openrisc.io/">openRISC&lt;/a> ), and open ISA (e.g. &lt;a href="http://www.riscv.org">RISC-V&lt;/a>), opportunities exist for developers to innovate on both side of the coin: in both hardware and software (i.e. &lt;strong>software-hardware co-design and development&lt;/strong>)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To properly supports software-hardware co-design for pre-silicon development, the embedded target must be able to host different hardware designs consisting of different ISA implementation (and sometimes more than one), HW IP(s) and peripherals, and on-chip topology.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Target execution platform(s)&lt;/strong> are platform devices with circuits that can be manipulated with hardware description language (HDL) to perform specific functions, including those of a microprocessor or a complete system on chip (SoC).&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="alert alert-primary" role="alert">
&lt;h4 class="alert-heading">Examples&lt;/h4>
&lt;em>
FPGA(s) are common target execution platforms used for prototyping and deployment. Emulators and arguably cycle-approximate instruction set simulators, used for verification and early software development, are other examples.
&lt;/em>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>In the context of pre-silicon development, &lt;em>programming&lt;/em> means either the manipulation of the device circuits with specific HDL (&lt;em>hardware programming&lt;/em>, or &lt;em>flashing&lt;/em>), or the loading of executable code and data (&lt;em>software programming&lt;/em>, or &lt;em>loading&lt;/em>) into the memory of the microprocessor that is executing on the target execution platform. XploR Studio supports both mode of programming support both pre and post silicon software development.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code class="language-plantuml" data-lang="plantuml">mainframe Target execution platform as the embedded target
state &amp;#34;Host Development System&amp;#34; as hosts
hosts : Linux or Windows on x86 / ia64
state &amp;#34;Pre-silicon target execution platform&amp;#34; as targets {
state JTAG
state &amp;#34;HDL programmable device&amp;#34; as HAPS {
state CPU : x86 or ARM
state Memory : DDR, SRAM, ...
state Peripherals : USB, Ethernet, ...
}
JTAG --&amp;gt; HAPS
}
note bottom of HAPS : CPU, Memory and Peripherals\nare (or can be) programmed with HDL.
state JTAG
note top of JTAG : JTAG used for both hardware\nand software programming
hosts -&amp;gt; JTAG
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h2 id="blueprints">Blueprints&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Blueprints are packages of hardware and/or software IP(s) that are bounded to specific &lt;em>execution platform&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-a-blueprint">What is a Blueprint?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>A blueprint is basically a combination of different IP(s), which can be either hardware or software-based or both. This design is what serves as the foundation of our embedded products.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="versatile-and-compatible">Versatile and Compatible&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>One appealing feature of blueprints is that they are incredibly versatile. For one, blueprints don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily have to be compatible among different hosts. This means that we can have both Windows and Linux blueprints, depending on what the situation calls for.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Moreover, they don&amp;rsquo;t have to be compatible between IDE versions. This makes the process of using blueprints more flexible and opens up options for our customers. They can opt for either Eclipse blueprint, Thea blueprint or even no blueprint at all.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="key-benefits-of-blueprints">Key Benefits of Blueprints&lt;/h3>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Provides a clear and concise plan: Blueprints serve as a detailed plan or a design that outlines the necessary steps and materials required to construct or create something. By having blueprints, it becomes easier to communicate technical information to our customers.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Ensures consistency in the final product: Blueprints help to ensure that the finished product is consistent with the original design and meets the expectations and requirements of our customers.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Saves time in the design process: With a blueprint in place, it becomes easier to identify potential issues and address them beforehand. This, in turn, saves time during the design process and can prevent costly mistakes.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="ide-integrated-development-environment">IDE: Integrated Development Environment&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>An Integrated Development Environment (IDE) is a software tool that provides everything necessary for a developer to write and debug code. An IDE typically includes a source code editor, a debugger, and a build automation tool. The XploR Studio IDE is a flexible and highly configurable software environment that helps RISC-V developers throughout the development process.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="toolchain">Toolchain&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In embedded development, a toolchain is a set of software tools that are used to compile, build, and debug code. The XploR Studio toolchain includes the LLVM compiler, GDB debugger, and openocd.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="llvm">LLVM&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>LLVM is a collection of modular and reusable compiler and toolchain technologies that are designed for software development. It uses an intermediate representation (IR) that is designed to be useful for a wide range of languages and target architectures. LLVM is used in the XploR Studio toolchain to compile code for RISC-V.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="gdb">GDB&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>GDB is a GNU project debugger that allows developers to debug programs written in various languages. It supports many debugging formats and offers many debugging features, including the ability to step through code, set breakpoints, and examine variables.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="rtos-real-time-operating-system">RTOS: Real-Time Operating System&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A real-time operating system (RTOS) is an operating system that is designed to provide predictable processing time for critical tasks. An RTOS can respond to an event in a specified time period. This makes it ideal for applications that require high reliability or timing precision.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="freertos">FreeRTOS&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>FreeRTOS is a popular open-source RTOS that provides a task scheduler and basic memory management. It supports many architectures, including RISC-V.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="zephyr">Zephyr&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Zephyr is an open-source RTOS that is designed for resource-constrained systems. It is scalable and offers many features, including a kernel that supports multiple threads, interrupt handling, and power management. It also supports many architectures, including RISC-V.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="openocd">OpenOCD&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Open On-Chip Debugger (OpenOCD) is an open-source software tool that provides debugging, in-system programming, and boundary scan testing for embedded devices. It supports many architectures and is used in the XploR Studio toolchain for debugging.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="quartus-programmer">Quartus Programmer&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Quartus Programmer is a tool that is used to program FPGA and ASIC devices. It can be used to download a configuration file to a specific device, such as the Intel Quartus FPGA.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="linux">Linux&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Linux is a free and open-source operating system that provides a stable and reliable platform for developers to build applications. It is widely used in embedded development and can be customized for specific applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="risc-v">RISC-V&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>RISC-V is an open-source instruction set architecture (ISA) that is designed to be scalable, modular, and extensible. It is used in many embedded systems, including the XploR Studio IDE.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="qemu">QEMU&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Quick Emulator (QEMU) is a free and open-source emulator that can emulate many architectures, including RISC-V. It is used in the XploR Studio IDE as the default target platform.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="fpga-field-programmable-gate-array">FPGA: Field-Programmable Gate Array&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>An FPGA is a programmable integrated circuit that can be configured by the user after manufacturing. It provides flexibility and can be used for prototyping and embedded development.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="asic-application-specific-integrated-circuit">ASIC: Application-Specific Integrated Circuit&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>An ASIC is an integrated circuit that is designed for a specific application. It provides higher performance than an FPGA but is less flexible.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Docs: Installation</title><link>/docs/getting-started/installation/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 08:49:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>/docs/getting-started/installation/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Docs: Quick start</title><link>/docs/getting-started/quick-start/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 08:49:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>/docs/getting-started/quick-start/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Docs: FAQ</title><link>/docs/getting-started/faq/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 08:49:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>/docs/getting-started/faq/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>